<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>com.github.marinm.songrec</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0+</project_license>
  <name>SongRec</name>
  <summary>An open-source, unofficial Shazam client for Linux, written in Rust.</summary>
  <description>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <p>- Recognize audio from an arbitrary audio file.</p>
    <p>- Recognize audio from the microphone.</p>
    <p>- Usage from both GUI and command line (for the file recognition part).</p>
    <p>- Provide an history of the recognized songs on the GUI, exportable to CSV.</p>
    <p>- Continuous song detection from the microphone, with the ability to choose your input device.</p>
    <p>- Ability to recognize songs from your speakers rather than your microphone (on compatible PulseAudio setups).</p>
    <p>- Generate a lure from a song that, when played, will fool Shazam into thinking that it is the concerned song.</p>
  </description>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/marin-m/SongRec/master/Screenshot.png</image>
      <caption>The GUI</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/marin-m/SongRec</url>
<!--
Open Age Rating Service
https://hughsie.github.io/oars/index.html
-->
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0" />
  <releases>
    <release version="0.1.6" date="2021-03-30">
      <description>
        <p>- Try to decode input files with FFMpeg when it is available on the target system, in order to support more audio and video formats when recognizing from a file.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.5" date="2021-03-26">
      <description>
        <p>- The song recognition history now has a right-click context menu that allows to copy the name of the songs, artists, tracks or albums, or to search previously recognized songs on YouTube.</p>
        <p>- It is now possible to select the name of the last recognized song so that it can be copy-pasted somewhere easily.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.4" date="2021-02-23">
      <description>
        <p>- Add the ability to recognize songs from your speakers rather than your microphone, through a checkbox that will be visible when the functionality is available, on compatible PulseAudio setups.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.3" date="2021-02-11">
      <description>
        <p>- Make the application fully responsive for mobile devices using GtkFlowBox, thanks to @a33k.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.2" date="2020-11-02">
      <description>
        <p>- Use GtkFileChooserNative so that the application is able to graphically pick files through Flatpak without requiring further file system permissions.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.1" date="2020-11-01">
      <description>
        <p>- Add Flatpak packaging scripts and assets.</p>
        <p>- Ensure that generated song lures don't last too long enough in certain cases.</p>
        <p>- Remove the dash in the long application ID as it was incompatible with Flatpak.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2020-10-07">
      <description>
        <p>Initial crates.io release</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
  <kudos>
    <!--
    GNOME Software kudos:
    https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gnome-software/blob/master/doc/kudos.md
    -->
    <kudo>ModernToolkit</kudo>
    <kudo>HiDpiIcon</kudo>
    <kudo>Notifications</kudo>
  </kudos>
  <developer_name>Marin</developer_name>
  <update_contact>marin-m@users.noreply.github.com</update_contact>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">com.github.marinm.songrec.desktop</launchable>
</component>
