<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>re.fossplant.songrec</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0+</project_license>
  <name>SongRec</name>
  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#DCB3E7</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#664D96</color>
  </branding>
  <summary>Recognize songs from audio easily</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="tr">Bir sesten şarkıları kolayca tanıyın</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sk-SK">Ľahko rozpoznávajte skladby zo zvukových záznamov</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr-FR">Reconnaître de la musique à partir d'audio facilement</summary>
  <description>
    <p>SongRec is an unofficial Shazam client for Linux, written in Rust. It allows you to easily recognize songs from your speakers, microphone or audio files.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">SongRec, Rust ile yazılmış gayri-resmi bir Shazam istemcisidir. Hoparlörünüzden, mikrofonunuzdan veya ses dosyalarınızdan kolayca şarkıları bulmanıza yardımcı olur.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">SongRec je neoficiálny klient pre Shazam určený pre Linux, napísaný v jazyku Rust. Umožňuje vám jednoducho rozpoznávať skladby z reproduktorov, mikrofónu alebo zvukových súborov.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">SongRec est un client Shazam non-officiel pour Linux, écrit en Rust. Il vous permet de reconnaître facilement des chansons à partir de vos hauts-parleurs, microphones ou fichiers audio.</p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">Özellikler:</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">Funkcie:</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">Fonctionnalités :</p>
    <p>- Recognize tracks from an arbitrary audio file.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">- Herhangi bir ses dosyasından şarkı tanıyabilir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Rozpozná zvuk z ľubovoľného zvukového súboru.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Reconnaître des chansons à partir d'un fichier audio arbitraire.</p>
    <p>- Recognize audio from the microphone.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Rozpozná zvuk z mikrofónu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Reconnaître des chansons à partir du microphone.</p>
    <p>- Usage from both GUI and command line.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Použitie prostredníctvom grafického rozhrania a aj z príkazového riadku.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Utilisable en mode graphique et depuis la ligne de commande.</p>
    <p>- Provide an history of the recognized songs on the GUI, exportable to CSV.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Zobrazuje históriu prehrávaných skladieb v grafickom rozhraní, ktorú je možné exportovať do formátu CSV.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Fournit un historique des chansons reconnues via l'interface graphique, exportable au format CSV.</p>
    <p>- Continuous song detection from the microphone, with the ability to choose your input device.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Nepretržité rozpoznávanie piesní z mikrofónu s možnosťou výberu vstupného zariadenia.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Reconnaissance continue de l'audio à partir du microphone, avec la possibilité de choisir votre périphérique d'entrée.</p>
    <p>- Ability to recognize songs from your speakers rather than your microphone.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk-SK">- Schopnosť rozpoznávať skladby z reproduktorov namiesto mikrofónu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr-FR">- Possibilité de reconnaître les chansons à partir de vos hauts-parleurs plutôt que votre microphone.</p>
  </description>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image type="source" scale="2">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/marin-m/SongRec/57bfe25/packaging/Screenshot_hires_light.png</image>
      <caption>SongRec's main window</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="sk-SK">Hlavné okno aplikácie SongRec</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="fr-FR">La fenêtre principale de SongRec</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image type="source" scale="2">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/marin-m/SongRec/57bfe25/packaging/Screenshot_favourites_light.png</image>
      <caption>SongRec's favourites window</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="sk-SK">Okno obľúbených položiek v aplikácii SongRec</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="fr-FR">La fenêtre des favoris de SongRec</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot environment="gnome:dark">
      <image type="source" scale="2">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/marin-m/SongRec/57bfe25/packaging/Screenshot_hires_dark.png</image>
      <caption>SongRec's main window, on GNOME in dark mode</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="sk-SK">Hlavné okno aplikácie SongRec v prostredí GNOME v tmavom režime</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="fr-FR">La fenêtre principale de SongRec, avec GNOME en mode sombre</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <translation type="gettext">songrec</translation>
  <replaces>
    <id>com.github.marinm.songrec</id>
  </replaces>
  <supports>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <control>touch</control>
  </supports>
  <recommends>
    <display_length compare="ge">360</display_length>
    <internet>always</internet>
  </recommends>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/marin-m/SongRec/issues</url>
  <url type="homepage">https://songrec.fossplant.re/</url>
  <url type="contact">https://matrix.to/#/#songrec:matrix.org</url>
  <url type="faq">https://github.com/marin-m/SongRec#readme</url>
  <url type="translate">https://github.com/marin-m/SongRec/tree/main/translations#readme</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/marin-m/SongRec</url>
  <!--
Open Age Rating Service
https://hughsie.github.io/oars/index.html
-->
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.6.9" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Skip using the PipeWire backend when no node is available (issue #265)</p>
        <p>Avoid a crash when using the CLI with MPRIS not loaded on the system</p>
        <p>Log network requests and responses when using the -vvv flag</p>
        <p>Log the command used by the ffmpeg backend when used</p>
        <p>Log the audio backend selected by CPAL on Linux</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.8" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Bump audio backend to CPAL 0.18 development version (see issues #257, #261)</p>
        <p>This means that libpipewire will be used by default on Linux (and hence be a dependency), fixing ALSA-related bugs</p>
        <p>Restore the official Windows build, with a new NSIS installer</p>
        <p>Update various Rust dependencies</p>
        <p>Use a larger volume gauge (PR #262 thanks to @wandabastyle)</p>
        <p>Push a first Turkish translation thanks to @Abrifq</p>
        <p>Remove the Symphonia ISO-MP4 parser as it seems buggy (issue #263)</p>
        <p>Also replace the MP3 and WAV parsers as they seem to incur misdetection with MP4</p>
        <p>Fix an use-after-free that may cause crash after removing a song from history (issue #259)</p>
        <p>Bump Flatpak GNOME runtime from version 49 to 50</p>
        <p>Enable back MPRIS by default on Linux</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.7" date="2026-03-25">
      <description>
        <p>Update dependencies, including using a non-deprecated library for the MPRIS module (issue #243)</p>
        <p>Use a monochrome tray icon for better GNOME integration (issue #255)</p>
        <p>Update the Brazilian translation thanks to @marcelocripe</p>
        <p>Update the Arabic translation thanks to @mu7basha</p>
        <p>Update the Slovak translation thanks to @dodog</p>
        <p>Update the Spanish translation thanks to @feramirez</p>
        <p>Allow shrinking down the window to arbitary sizes in windowed mode</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.6" date="2026-03-08">
      <description>
        <p>Fix translations other than fr_FR not being loaded in the Flatpak build (see issue #247)</p>
        <p>Make extra Pulseaudio-related debugging output to be displayed when -v is passed, to allow troubleshoot SongRec not working on Snap with the Ubuntu 26.04+ kernel (see issue #111)</p>
        <p>Prepare supporting CPAL 0.18+ which will have libpulse and libpipewire backends (that adds dependencies in the install instructions which are not actually used for the moment)</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.5" date="2026-03-07">
      <description>
        <p>Update the Czech translation thanks to @Fjuro</p>
        <p>Update the Dutch translation thanks to @Vistaus</p>
        <p>Fix cross-platform support and building without the GUI (issue #231)</p>
        <p>Fix legacy command line support (PR #233 thanks to @bodoque-01)</p>
        <p>Update the Slovak translation (PR #237 thanks to @dodog)</p>
        <p>Update the Russian translation (PR #239 thanks to @AlexanderShad)</p>
        <p>Implement Snapcraft compatibility (issues #111 and #244)</p>
        <p>Update the Arabic translation thanks to @mu7basha</p>
        <p>Update the "rodio" dependency and make the ALSA device names look native</p>
        <p>Select history rows only after a left-click to better match the native GTK-4 behavior (issue #245)</p>
        <p>Handle the Context key and Ctrl+C key bindings when an history row is selected (issues #245 and #200)</p>
        <p>Fix supporting MPRIS over Flatpak (issue #214)</p>
        <p>Handle left-clicks on the system tray icon over KDE</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.4" date="2026-02-19">
      <description>
        <p>Add an UI button to refresh the PulseAudio device list</p>
        <p>Add a status icon through the KSNI rust crate</p>
        <p>Add a no duplicate entries setting (issue #198)</p>
        <p>Set the default request interval to a tunable 8 seconds</p>
        <p>Don't try to fingerprint empty audio buffers</p>
        <p>Fix a display glitch</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.3" date="2026-02-18">
      <description>
        <p>Reduce song history load time when the history is large (issue #224)</p>
        <p>Drop reqwest for libsoup for network requests, this will make the binary and the compile time smaller</p>
        <p>Make the network code asynchronous (issue #223)</p>
        <p>Increase the default request interval from 4 to 10 seconds to decrease the odds of rate-limiting, and make it fully configurable (issues #222, #154, #164, #218)</p>
        <p>Try a colorful icon</p>
        <p>Implement more standard shortcuts for GNOME Circle criteria compliance</p>
        <p>Add Snapcraft compatibility</p>
        <p>Move command line output to the new fern-based logging system</p>
        <p>Add a --list-devices flag for CLI commands like "listen" and "recognize"</p>
        <p>Add a --request-interval flag for CLI commands like "listen" and "recognize"</p>
        <p>Avoid to spam the debugging output with huge raw song cover data</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.2" date="2026-02-15">
      <description>
        <p>Avoid stack overflow when compiling in debug mode on Linux</p>
        <p>Add support building the GTK 4 nativaly for Ubuntu 24.04 LTS in addition to 25.04, 25.10 and Flatpak</p>
        <p>Use a steel icon matching the recommended bounds for a Flathub icon</p>
        <p>Synchronize Czech, Brazilian and French translations (thanks to @Fjuro and @marcelocripe)</p>
        <p>Add copiable debug information in the About panel</p>
        <p>Add UI settings for the amp.shazam buffer size and recognition interval (see issues #154, #164, #81)</p>
        <p>Notify users about the rate limit status</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.1.1" date="2026-02-14">
      <description>
        <p>Use a flat-looking icon consistent with both the previous releases of SongRec and the GNOME UI guidelines</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.1" date="2026-02-14">
      <description>
        <p>Improve accessibility</p>
        <p>Update metainfo.xml to better fit the GNOME Circle and Flathub guidelines</p>
        <p>Move translations to Weblate (weblate.fossplant.re)</p>
        <p>Auto-generate manpage files</p>
        <p>Add CI and DOAP files</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.0" date="2026-02-12">
      <description>
        <p>Update interface to GTK 4 (issue #206)</p>
        <p>Fix using MPRIS over Flatpak (issue #214)</p>
        <p>Add advanced logs using the -v command line flag</p>
        <p>Update upstream translations (Czech by @Fjuro, Brazilian by @marcelocripe)</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.0" date="2026-01-21">
      <description>
        <p>Packaging: Change the translations path to /usr/share/locale instead of /usr/share/songrec/translations (this may require action from distribution package maintainers)</p>
        <p>Packaging: Change the package name to re.fossplant.songrec instead of com.github.marinm.songrec so that the application can be correctly verified on Flathub</p>
        <p>Branding: Update the Flathub landing page to comply with style guidelines</p>
        <p>Branding: Change the project homepage URL</p>
        <p>Wrap the name of long microphone devices names in the GUI</p>
        <p>Handle network-related variables correctly (PR #191 thanks to @losynix)</p>
        <p>Fix the chronological order when displaying songs onto the UI (PR #192 thanks to @nt8r)</p>
        <p>Add Russian translation (PR #193 thanks to @AlexanderShad)</p>
        <p>Rectify the window icon under Wayland (PR #203 thanks to @Integral-Tech)</p>
        <p>Add the recognition date to favorites window, and made all columns sortable (PR #208 thanks to @damonhayhurst)</p>
        <p>Fix MPRIS cover art display under certain platforms (PR #210 thanks to @micahlt)</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.3" date="2024-09-29">
      <description>
        <p>Prevent mission application icon when running (PR #163 thanks to @heldderarbeit)</p>
        <p>Quit the application when doing Ctrl+Q (issue #181)</p>
        <p>Change the Flatpak permission from --device=dri to --device=all, because --device=dri made it impossible to change the audio input source to monitor mode on certain recent Flatpak/PipeWire combinations (issue #177)</p>
        <p>Fix usage of the Context menu in the Favourites window (PR #179 from @damonhayhurst and issue #178)</p>
        <p>Minor code refactoring (PR #153 from @dotX12) and bug fixes, including with building in --debug mode (issue #159)</p>
        <p>Remove the "Play Shazam lure" button, as it is no more functional with recent Shazam versions (issue #170)</p>
        <p>Update Slovak translation from issue #23 (thanks to @dodog)</p>
        <p>Update Portuguese translation from PR #172 (thanks to @marcelocripe)</p>
        <p>Update the `rodio` crate dependency to drop the requirement on the `minimp3` library, that prevented building on certain platforms</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.2" date="2024-01-22">
      <description>
        <p>Add a Catalan translation (thanks to @pgiuli in issue #23)</p>
        <p>Make the UI more clear so that it is visible that we are toggling the recognition from the speakers rather than the microphone when the monitor mode is on (see issue #149)</p>
        <p>Fix a bug that had certain strings to be mistakenly copied at the bad places in the internationalized versions of the application, due to the fuzzy mode of msgmerge/gettext</p>
        <p>Update the Dutch translation (thanks to @Vistaus in PR #150)</p>
        <p>Update compilation instructions in the README.md file</p>
        <p>Allow to compile the app with the libpulse and MPRIS module enabled on non-Linux UNIX systems such as BSD (see issue #152)</p>
        <p>Possibly improve the compatibility of the recognize-from-speakers feature</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.1" date="2024-01-14">
      <description>
        <p>Add a Korean translation (thanks to @MarongHappy in PR #146)</p>
        <p>Re-integrate MPRIS compatibility code in the default builds, with an opt-in GUI option</p>
        <p>Add a simple preference window and an about dialog</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2023-12-24">
      <description>
        <p>Use libpulse (when available) for displaying the list of selectable audio input devices by default, instead of alsalib for listing audio inputs and pactl for switching to a monitor mode device, so that the list of devices displays correct values on PipeWire/PulseAudio-based systems.</p>
        <p>Make the dependencies over libpulse and DBus MPRIS fully optional, through Cargo features.</p>
        <p>Disable MPRIS signalling in default builds, as it may interfer inopportunely with media keys control from other media players (as submitted in issue #89)</p>
        <p>Fix build issues on non-Linux platforms (thanks to pull request #144 from @dotX12)</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.3" date="2023-10-15">
      <description>
        <p>Add a Favourite songs list in the interface (thanks to pull request #123 from @damonhayhurst)</p>
        <p>Add a Spanish UI translation (as submitted by @Swyter in issue #23)</p>
        <p>Add a German UI translation (as submitted in issue #23)</p>
        <p>Update the Italian UI translation (thanks to pull request #133 from @M0Rf30)</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.2" date="2022-05-26">
      <description>
        <p>Add a checkbox into the graphical interface in order to disable or enable system notifications whenever recognizing a song (thanks to @damonhayhurst).</p>
        <p>Fix the bug that previously caused the Firefox user interface menus to blink on Linux after the "Search on YouTube" feature has been used (thanks to @ducaton).</p>
        <p>Update the French translation.</p>
        <p>Add safety checks in order to prevent potential crashes when handling corrupt configuration files or invalid audio devices.</p>
        <p>Change the path of the files saving user interface-related preferences in order to update a deprecated Rust crate (this may create a symbolic link from "~/.local/share/songrec" towards an preexisting "~/.local/share/SongRec" directory under Linux).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2022-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>- Fix the behavior of the new "recognize" command, when recognizing from a file.</p>
        <p>- Add album artwork, if it exists, to the desktop notification when a song is recognized (thanks to @damonhayhurst).</p>
        <p>- Update the Dutch translation (thanks to @Vistaus).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2021-12-26">
      <description>
        <p>- Introduce a new command-line interface allowing to use microphone recognition from the command line, with the "recognize" and "listen" commands (thanks to @Hummer12007), keeping older command backwards compatibility.</p>
        <p>- Update the CSV export format in order to introduce new "track_key", "release_year" and "genre" columns (thanks to @tyd), where "track_key" is an identifier internal to the Shazam database.</p>
        <p>- Allow exposing song metadata through the standard DBus MPRIS interface (thanks to @Hummer12007).</p>
        <p>- Improve source code structure in order to split the dual CLI/GUI parts from the core thread communication and fingerprinting parts and from other platform-dependant utility code.</p>
        <p>- Update certain dependent crates to more recent minor versions, among other possible things in order to accept a higher LibreSSL version.</p>
        <p>- Add the program version without the program help output (see the "-h" or "-V", "--version" options).</p>
        <p>- Add a Polish translation (thanks to @qarmin).</p>
        <p>- Update the French translation according to recent changes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.1" date="2021-10-04">
      <description>
        <p>- Don't crash when there is no input device available on the host machine.</p>
        <p>- Update the Dutch translation.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2021-08-27">
      <description>
        <p>- Add Japanese and Italian translations.</p>
        <p>- Fix PipeWire compatibility.</p>
        <p>- Add support for a possible XDG action for recognizing from a file.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.9" date="2021-08-20">
      <description>
        <p>- Add French and Dutch translations.</p>
        <p>- Ensure that only one window of SongRec is present.</p>
        <p>- Avoid to display "No match for this song" when multiple instances of SongRec would be displayed and one would be closed.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.8" date="2021-06-01">
      <description>
        <p>- Include a "Cargo.lock" file in the project so that it can be accepted in certain packaging systems that require freezing Rust dependencies to a known subversion.</p>
        <p>- Change the locale sent in HTTP requests to avoid to display internationalized song titles, in certain cases.</p>
        <p>- Fix a minor typo in the algorithm implementation that shouldn't impact recognition.</p>
        <p>- Improve portability.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.7" date="2021-04-09">
      <description>
        <p>- Display a clean "Shazam servers are not reachable, are you connected?" message on the GUI when the computer has been offline, rather than showing low-level errors.</p>
        <p>- Improve cross-platform support.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.6" date="2021-03-30">
      <description>
        <p>- Try to decode input files with FFMpeg when it is available on the target system, in order to support more audio and video formats when recognizing from a file.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.5" date="2021-03-26">
      <description>
        <p>- The song recognition history now has a right-click context menu that allows to copy the name of the songs, artists, tracks or albums, or to search previously recognized songs on YouTube.</p>
        <p>- It is now possible to select the name of the last recognized song so that it can be copy-pasted somewhere easily.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.4" date="2021-02-23">
      <description>
        <p>- Add the ability to recognize songs from your speakers rather than your microphone, through a checkbox that will be visible when the functionality is available, on compatible PulseAudio setups.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.3" date="2021-02-11">
      <description>
        <p>- Make the application fully responsive for mobile devices using GtkFlowBox, thanks to @a33k.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.2" date="2020-11-02">
      <description>
        <p>- Use GtkFileChooserNative so that the application is able to graphically pick files through Flatpak without requiring further file system permissions.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.1" date="2020-11-01">
      <description>
        <p>- Add Flatpak packaging scripts and assets.</p>
        <p>- Ensure that generated song lures don't last too long enough in certain cases.</p>
        <p>- Remove the dash in the long application ID as it was incompatible with Flatpak.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2020-10-07">
      <description>
        <p>Initial crates.io release</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
  <developer id="re.fossplant">
    <name>Marin M. - Fossplant.re</name>
  </developer>
  <update_contact>marin-m@users.noreply.github.com</update_contact>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">re.fossplant.songrec.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <id>com.github.marinm.songrec</id>
    <dbus type="user">re.fossplant.songrec</dbus>
    <binary>songrec</binary>
    <mediatype>audio/mpeg</mediatype>
    <mediatype>audio/x-wav</mediatype>
    <mediatype>audio/x-vorbis+ogg</mediatype>
    <mediatype>audio/flac</mediatype>
  </provides>
</component>
